Niko Strongioglou

4 +41(0)787042239

♀ Salerstrasse 16, 8050 Zurich

♥ web in linkedIn ♥ github 🕏 leetCode 💟 email

I am a software engineer with 10 years of experience building large-scale, data-intensive, distributed systems. I revel in being a member of teams composed of smart, self-motivated, and inspired people who consider Computer Science as a means of changing the world.

Professional Experience

Senior Software Engineer at 1PlusX/TripleLift Zurich, Switzerland May 2020 - Present Data management and analytics platform providing multi-dimensional batch and real-time user tracking and profiling. Data consolidation and Audience teams.

- Management of various multi-sprint/multi-quarter and cross-team data projects: Leading and mentoring small groups of developers while resolving ambiguity with non-engineering dependencies (e.g. legal, product, customer success, external clients)
- Created or maintained 50+ unique data pipelines running on production systems with more than 2PB of daily loads (spawning 30-40k Spark jobs daily).
- Extensive work on AWS. Developed and maintained Terraform infra of hundreds of services.
- Tag manager ingestion restructuring resulting in a data-set specific size decrease of up to 80% while maintaining targeting quality.
- Decreased pipeline runtime up to 15% by introducing batch REST API endpoints.
- Close collaboration with ML engineers to deliver useful data for their pipelines MLOps.
- Cross-team user ID storage optimization resulting in up to 20% decrease in Couchbase loads. Load on external APIs was decreased up to 40%.
- Data privacy pipelines: Access and deletion requests' handling of multiple protocols (GDPR, CCPA).
- DSL design for ETL ops: Rich syntax for creating and combining attributes.
- Real-time data ingestion infrastructure design able to accommodate 7.5M unique events per second.
- E2E user tracking: From cookies and browser-side SDKs to graph-based ID management.
- UI work on analytics dashboards, widgets, data pipeline builder.



Software Engineer at Veezoo AG Zurich, Switzerland

March 2019 - May 2020

NLP platform providing analytics through a variety of corporate data source integrations - namely Oracle, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Salesforce, IBM DB2, Hadoop, SAP HANA - using a QA interface.

- Knowledge graph ontology representations API for (non)-relational data sources which automated data onboarding.
- Semantic parsing pipelines for natural languages (bag of words to logical forms to SQL generation).
- Extend and maintain the Duckling language engine

Software Engineer at Locatee AG *Zurich, Switzerland* April 2017 - March 2019 Analytics platform providing hyperlocation, real-time workspace occupancy insights and predictive APIs through geospatial data scraping (SNMP protocol).

• Led the modularization of the core app monolith. From creating three distinct services - Analytics API, Data processing service, and pollers - to POCs and eventually to global roll-outs.

(Java 8) (Spring Core) (MySQL) (InfluxDB) (Tableau) (Neo4J) (Kafka) (Python) (Jupyter) (Pandas) (Docker)

- Online data distillation pipeline detecting outliers on workspace behavior and identifying team collaboration coefficients.
- Different MySQL read/write optimizations for measurements post-processing

Software Engineer at Upstream Systems SA Athens, Greece October 2014 - March 2017 Green-field project re-engineering the core CRM platform as a fully distributed system. The implementation included a multitude of APIs for data streaming and job scheduling accommodating thousands to millions of transactions daily.

- Asynchronous event-driven services on distributed environments using Guava and RabbitMQ. High availability and resiliency optimizations.
- Implementation of Elasticsearch user samplers via Groovy scripts and custom treemap algorithms. Stretch testing, benchmarking, and performance tweaking on Elasticsearch operations.
- Performance profiling (Dropwizard's Metrics, YourKit, Grafana, and other tools).
- API versioning (URL & Resource Representation).
- Batch job framework implementation with RabbitMQ and Quartz. Throttling and flow control features included.
- QA Automation framework (Selenium, Spring).
- Recommendation engine using Mahout and supervised learning regression algorithms (Log Likelihood Similarity for item-based recommender and Pearson correlation similarity for user-based recommender).



Software Engineer at Accenture Athens, Greece

June 2014 - September 2014

Provisioning and mediation over Oracle databases and mobile telecom software.

TOAD (SQL Developer) (WebLogic)

Freelancing Web Developer Athens, Greece

January 2012 - November 2013

Software development on static content pages and web applications.

HTML / CSS Bootstrap Javascript JQuery Angular JS

Other Works

- Designer and developer of a B+ indexed RDBMS in C.
- Co-creator of a social network based on node.js and socket.io. The network provided real-time chatting and financial transactions between users.
- Various API prototypes using Flask and FastAPI. [1] [2]

Education

Degrees

September M.Sc. in Computer Science

2013 Department of Computer Science, National and Kapodistrian University of

Athens - 7.49/10 or Upper Second-Class Honours

Languages

Greek Native

English Certificate of Proficiency in English, University of Cambridge, Grade A

Certificate of Proficiency in English, University of Michigan, Honors

German B1

French Diplome d'etudes en langue Française (DELF)

References